{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This U.S. immigrant'searlyventuresincludedinvestmentsinAdamsExpressandthe founding of the Keystone Bridge Company. After selling his largest company to J.P. Morgan, this author of the \"Gospel of Wealth\" created a namesake foundation to establish libraries and research councils. Making most of his wealth as a steel magnate, for ten points, what Scottish-born American philanthropist built an eponymous concert hall in New York City?",
      "answer": "AndrewCarnegie"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cave paintings in the Acacus [[ah-KAH-kus]] Mountains indicate this desert may only have formed after the last Ice Age. The Tibesti mountains lie in this desert, which in recent decades has advanced south into the Sahel [[sah-HEEL]]. Peoples including the Berbers and the Tuareg [[TWAH-reg]] led gold and salt caravans across this desert. Historically crossed by Bedouin caravans, for ten points, what is this massive desert in northern Africa? ANSWER:SaharaDesert (or aṣ-ṣaḥrāʼal-kubrá) (3) This woman's actions at Werowocomoco [[way-ruh-wah-KOH-muh-koh]] are detailed in a letter to Queen Anne of Denmark. This womandiedaftertravellingtoEngland with her husband, John Rolfe, ten years after she intervenedinanexecutionorderedbyher father, the Powhatan [[POW-uh-tan]] chief. For ten points, name this Native American \"princess\" who supposedly saved the life of John Smith during the first year of Jamestown. ANSWER:Pocahontas(acceptMatoaka; accept RebeccaRolfebefore \"Rolfe\" is mentioned) (4) This structure's \"Robber's Tunnel\" was likely resealed during the Ramesside Restoration, one of many ancient sites refurbished by the sitting government. Atthefootof this structure is a preserved solar barque [[BARK]]knownasKhufu'sShip.Firstbuiltinthe 26th Century BC, this building stood as the tallest structure in the world until the construction of the Lincoln Cathedral in 1311. For ten points, namethisEgyptiantomband \"Ancient Wonder of the World.\" ANSWER:Great Pyramidof Giza (acceptPyramidofKhufu;orPyramidofCheops) 2021-22 C Set History (5) During Operation Iskra, Kirill Meretskov [[meh-RET-skof]] conducted an effort to open this city to a supply route known as the \"Road of Life.\" In conjunction with Finland, Nazi Germany's Army Group North besieged this city for two and half years during World War Two. The outbreak of World War One led to this city being renamed Petrograd. The Hermitage and Winter Palace are in, for ten points, what one-time capital of Imperial Russia? ANSWER:St. Petersburg(orLeningrad; acceptPetrogradbefore mentioned) (6) During this conflict, the The Sun's headline \"Gotcha\" caused controversy for downplaying its casualties. Operation Rosario, ordered by Leopoldo Galtieri [[gahl-TYEH-ree]], began this war, which included an engagement between the General Belgrano and the HMS Conqueror. Margaret Thatcher and her War Cabinet quickly recaptured South Georgia during this conflict. The UK and Argentina vied for control of a namesake Atlantic archipelago in, for ten points, what ten-week war in 1982? ANSWER:Falklands Wars (accept War of theFalklandIslands; accept La Guerra de las Malvinas) (7) A member of this religioussectnamedAlicePaulservedaspresidentoftheNational Women's Party. The only U.S. president tofollowthisdenomination'steachingswasRichard Nixon. This sect's persecution in England ledWilliamPenntorequestthatJamesIIgivehim and his followers land in the New World. For ten points, name this pacifist Christian sect more formally known as the Society of Friends. ANSWER:Quakers (accept Society ofFriendsbeforementioned; prompt on \"Christianity\") (8) This politicianopenlycriticizedfellowpartymemberJoeManchinforusingtheterm \"young lady\" while refuting her claims on his lack of transparency in negotiating with oil lobbyists. This congresswoman, who wore a dress emblazoned with the words \"Tax the Rich\" to the 2021 Met Gala, is the youngest woman to take a seat in the House of Representatives, at the age of 29. For ten points, name this Puerto Rican-descended New York Representative sometimes known by her initials AOC.",
      "answer": "AlexandriaOcasio-CortezacceptAOCbeforementioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "This musician, who embarked on the Never Ending Tourin1988,releasedthe1979 album Slow Train Coming following his conversion to Evangelical Christianity. This artist included \"A Hard Rain's a-Gonna Fall\" on his seminal album titled The Freewheelin' [this artist]. The author of such folk hits as \"The Times They Are a-Changin'\"and\"Blowin'inthe Wind,\" for ten points, who is this winner of the 2016 Nobel Prize in Literature?",
      "answer": [
        "BobDylan",
        "RobertDylan",
        "RobertAllenZimmerman 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city, millwright Rufus Putnam created effective prefabricated fortifications prior to the battle of Dorchester Heights. Henry Knox dragged cannons captured at Fort Ticonderoga to assist in Washington's capture of this city. William Prescott and Israel Putnam led a faileddefenseofBreed'sHillduringThomasGage's1775assaultonthiscity.A 1770 \"Massacre\" occurred in, for ten points, what New England city,thesiteoftheBattleof Bunker Hill? ANSWER:Boston BONUS: Which future U.S president successfully earned the acquittal of the perpetrators of the Boston Massacre as a lawyer in their 1770 trial? ANSWER:JohnAdams(prompt on \"Adams\") (2) Using an aquarium, filmmaker Georges Méliès [[mel-YAY]] simulated exploring this ship's wreckageina19thcenturysilentshortfilm.The1898DelPeral[[peh-RAHL]]Inquiry found that this ship's demise was not caused by hitting a mine. In an example of \"yellow journalism,\" this ship's name was rhymed with the phrase \"To Hell with Spain\" by the U.S. press. For ten points, name thiscruiserwhosesinkinginHavanaHarborwasanimpetusfor the Spanish-American War.",
        "answer": "USSMaine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This newspaper magnate and inspiration for the film Citizen Kane used the Maine tragedy as a way to bolster sales during the Circulation Wars with Joseph Pulitzer.",
        "answer": "William RandolphHearst"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man made a 300-mile long journey to Delagoa Bay following hisescapefroma Boer prison camp. The disaster of the Dardanelles campaign, especially the Battle of Gallipoli [[gah-LIH-poh-lee]], led to this man's resignation as First Lord of the Admiralty. Following the Dunkirk evacuation, this PM gave the \"This was their finest hour\" speech to the House of Commons. For ten points, name this prime minister of the UK during the majority of World War Two.",
        "answer": "WinstonChurchillor Sir Winston LeonardSpencerChurchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Churchill served as War Secretary to this prime minister of Welsh descent who made up the Big Three at Versailles with Georges Clemenceau [[kleh-mahn-SOH]] and Woodrow Wilson.",
        "answer": "DavidLloyd George"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this dynasty, the oldest still-extant wooden building in the world, the Buddhist Nanchan Temple, was built. This dynasty failed to assert control overtheFergana Valley following a military defeat by the Abbasids at the Talas River. The An Lushan Rebellion hastened the fall of this dynasty, and EmpressWubrieflyinterrupteditinthelate 7th century. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty which succeeded the Sui [[SWEE]] and was followed by the Song. ANSWER:TangDynasty (accept DàTáng; or GreatTang) BONUS: This Chinese technology may have been passed to the West by Chinese prisoners captured bytheAbbasidsduringtheBattleofTalasRiver.Thismaterialwasoftenmadewith pulp and used for painting and calligraphy. ANSWER:Papermaking (5) Cicero [[SIH-seh-roh]] called this city's general Epaminondas [[eh-pah-mih-NAHN-duss]], who fell at the Battle of Mantinea [[mahn-tih-NEH-ah]], the \"First Man of Greece.\" Until theirdefeatatChaeronea[[kay-roh-NAY-uh]],aunitof300male lovers called the Sacred Band defended this city. This city-state, which was legendarily founded by Cadmus, was fought over by thetwosonsofOedipusinSevenAgainst[thiscity]. For ten points, name this Boeotian [[boe-EE-shuhn]] city-state which shares its name with an ancient Egyptian capital. ANSWER:Thebes(acceptThebai; orThiva) BONUS: This father of Alexander theGreatcrushedGreekresistanceagainstMacedonatthe Battle of Chaeronea. ANSWER:PhilipII of Macedon (orFílippos ó Makedõn) (6) This politician had three electoral votes cast for him in the 2016 election from the state of Washington. This man became National Security Adviser for Reagan in the wakeof the Iran-Contra Scandal. Following the January Capitol attacks, this politician publicly left the Republican Party. This man died from COVID-19 complications at Walter Reed hospital in October of 2021. The Secretary of State during the first George W. Bush administration was, for ten points, which four-star general?",
        "answer": "ColinPowellor Colin LutherPowell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What \"massacre\" of Vietnamese citizens by U.S. troops under William Calley was allegedly \"whitewashed\" by a then 31-year old Colin Powell? ANSWER:My Lai[[MEE \"LIE\"]] Massacre 2021-22 C Set History (7) Theia [[THAY-uh]] was one of thesebeings,whowithherconsort,Hyperion,birthed Eos [[AY-ohs]], Selene, and Helios. One of these beings, Iapetus [[\"eye\"-AP-ih-tus]],fathered the figures who respectively gave humans fire and who held up theworld,Prometheusand Atlas. The most powerful of these beings was thehusbandofRhea[[RAY-uh]]andcastrated his father, Uranus, before being defeated and cast into Tartarus. For ten points, name these pre-Olympian gods who were overthrown by Zeus and his siblings. ANSWER:Titans (acceptTitanes; acceptTitanides) BONUS: Another Titan, Mnemosyne [[neh-MAH-sih-nee]], embodied memory and was the mother of what group of nine goddesses who inspired the humanities and sciences? ANSWER:Muses (orMousai) (8) In this nation, Inaka [[ee-NAH-kah]] is a term for people who live in small hamlets far from major metropolitan areas. An eighth-century Shugendo monk was the first to summit one of this nation's \"Three Holy Mountains,\" Mount Haku. Every twenty years, this nation's pilgrimage site, the Ise [[EE-seh]] Grand Shrine, is rebuilt to represent death and renewal in the Shinto faith. The cities of Osaka and Nagasaki are found in, for ten points, what East Asian nation? ANSWER:Japan(acceptNippon-koku orNihon-koku) BONUS: Another holy mountain in Japan is this summit seen in a series of ukiyo-e works titledThirty-Six Views of[this mountain].",
        "answer": "MountFujiorFujisan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Westward Expansion in the United States",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Treaty which ended the Mexican-American War, adding the territories of California, New Mexico, and Arizona.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty ofGuadalupe Hidalgo",
            "TreatyofPeace, Friendship, Limits and Settlementbetween the United States of America andthe Mexican Republic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Editor and presidential candidate who said \"Go West, Young Man.\"",
          "answer": "HoraceGreeley"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "October Revolution",
      "prompt": "Concerning the October Revolution, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Soviet Union who led the Bolsheviks during the revolution.",
          "answer": "Vladimir IlychLeninor Vladimir IlyichUlyanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trudovik president of the Provisional Government and leader of the prior February Revolution.",
          "answer": "AlexanderKerenskyor Alexander FyodorovichKerensky"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. journalist buried in the Kremlin who recounted events inTen Days that Shook the World.",
          "answer": "John \"Jack\"Reedor John \"Jack\" SilasReed 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Slave Revolts in the Americas",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Only nation to gain independence via a slave revolt, led by Toussaint L'Overture [[too-SAHNT loh-vehr-TYOOR]] and Jean-Jacques Dessalines [[deh-sah-LEEN]].",
          "answer": [
            "Republic ofHaiti",
            "République d'Haïti",
            "Repiblik dAyiti"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Abolitionist who aimed to start a slave revolt through his raid on Harpers Ferry.",
          "answer": "JohnBrown"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ne Win of Myanmar may have been trained by the last of these people. Ten of these people formed a group of \"Braves,\" and some used a tool named for \"water spiders.\" In one incident, these people replicated Mon lamps in (20 pts)",
        "an attack. Nightingale floors were intended to expose these people, whose training likely originated with the Iga clan in the Kansai region. Often shown with star-shaped (10 pts)",
        "shuriken, for ten points, who were these stealthyJapanese mercenaries? ANSWER:Ninja(acceptShinobi;Monomi; orNokizaru) (2) This city celebrates Three Flags Day, which commemorates the two days in 1804 on which the French, Spanish, and U.S. flags flew over it during the Louisiana Purchase. This host of the (+) 1904 Olympics is near Cahokia Mounds andcontainsa monument to westward expansion, the Gateway(*)Arch.AFrenchkingisthenamesake of, for ten points, what largest city in Missouri? ANSWER:St. Louis (3) In this nation, the nau cargo ship known as Nossa Senhora sank in its longest river whilecarryingpeppercornsbackfromIndia.Inthe15thcentury,AfonsoIIIfrom the House of Aviz styled himself ruler of this one-time (+) kingdom and the recently conquered region of Algarve [[al-GAR-veh]]. The expedition to Ceuta [[seh-YOO-tah]] was launched from this nation's city of Porto by HenrytheNavigator.(*)Forthepoint, identify this European country on the Iberian Peninsula, governed from Lisbon. ANSWER:Portugal(acceptPortugueseRepublic; or RepúblicaPortuguesa); accept Kingdom ofPortugal) (4) A group of Democrats with this name nominated former Republican John M. Palmer as their presidential candidate in 1896. An 1869 \"Panic\" over this good occurred after investors Jay Gould and James(+)Fiskattemptedtocorneritsmarket. At the 1896 DNC, bimetallism supporter William Jennings Bryan delivered a speech stating \"you shall not crucify mankind upon a cross of\" (*) [this good]. For ten points, name this precious metal whose \"Standard\" was abandoned by Richard Nixon. ANSWER:Gold(acceptAu; acceptGoldDemocrats; accept\"Cross ofGold\" speech) (5) This figure may have invented the plot in which Royalist Cécile Renault [[ray-NOH]] hid two small knivesinabaginanattempttokillhim.Withsupportfrom the Garde National, the faction known as the Thermidorians ousted (+) thismanand sent him to the guillotine [[GEE-yoh-teen]]. The \"Reign of Terror\" was (*)overseenby, for ten points, which radical lawyer and head of the Committee of Public Safety during the French Revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": "MaximilienRobespierreor Maximilien FrançoisMarie Isidore deRobespierre 2021-22 C Set History"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The body of this nation'sKingAlexanderIwasthrownoffabalconyofthe\"Old Palace\" during its May Coup, whichreplacedhimwithPeterI.AlongsideRomaniaand Greece, this nation seized territory from Bulgaria during (20 pts)",
        "the Second Balkan War. Austria-Hungary gave this smaller nation the JulyUltimatumafternationalistGavrilo Princip killed Archduke FranzFerdinandinBosnia (10 pts)",
        ".Fortenpoints,namethisBalkan nation, the most populous constituent of the former Yugoslavia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic ofSerbiaor RepublikaSrbija",
        "acceptKingdom ofSerbia",
        "or Kraljevina Srbija"
      ]
    }
  ]
}